Guide to the William Downie Papers Relating to Exploration of British Columbia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Downie papers relating to exploration of British Columbia
1858-1906
WA MSS S-2490
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.43
(4 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Papers consist of diaries, correspondence, writings, printed works, photographs, maps, and other materials that document William Downie's life, interest, and travels in the Northwest, particularly during the 1850s and 1860s. The papers offer evidence of early exploration and mining operations in British Columbia, particularly in the Quesnel Forks area by the Quesnelle Mining Company. Downie's interest and encounters with indigenous inhabitants are recorded.
3.43 linear ft. (4 boxes) + 1 broadside
Downie, William, 1819-1893
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kenneth R. Graham, 2003 and 2004. Gift of Graham C. Boettcher and Lindsay A. Boettcher, 2005 addition. Gift of Graham C. Boettcher, 2006 addition.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM DOWNIE (1819-1894)
William Downie was born in Glasgow, Scotland in 1819. He worked as sailor before joining the Gold Rush in San Francisco in 1849. He mined near Sacramento and along the Yuba River in California, in British Columbia (where he studied Canadian Indians and made reports to the Canadian government about the topography of the land around the Skeena River and the British Columbia coastline), and in Panama. He founded the California town of Downieville, California's first state capitol. A volume of his reminiscences, Hunting for Gold, was published in 1893 by the California Publishing Company in San Francisco. He died in San Francisco in 1894.
Scope and Contents
The William Downie Papers Relating to Exploration of British Columbia consist of diaries, correspondence, writings, printed works, photographs, and other material that document William Downie's life, interest, and travels in the Northwest during the 1850s and 1860s. The papers offer evidence of early exploration and mining in British Columbia, particularly in the Quesnel Forks area, one of the oldest mining camps in the Cariboo district. Downie's interest in, and encounters with, British Columbia's indigenous inhabitants are also recorded.
Series I. Diaries is comprised of seven manuscript diaries that document Downie's travels in British Columbia and the Northwest. The earliest volume, recorded in an 1856 Union Diary, was mainly kept by Downie during the summer and early fall of 1858 while in Nanaimo. A diary dated 1859 Sept 10 to Sept 20 relates an exploratory canoe journey along the Skeena River, with comments about geography, mining prospects, Indian traveling companions, and local Indian customs. Loose notes from 1860 Apr 16 to Apr 20 relate a Nass River prospecting trip, and record impressions of William Duncan and his mission at Fort Stimpson as well as descriptions of several Indian village. These notes, originally discovered in the 1859 diary, are foldered separately.
A bound volume, titled "Family Register", bears an inscription to Downie from James Duneau, 1860 Jan 3. The volume contains Downie's dated diary entries from January to November 1860, as well as two sketched maps: one of the "South Channel" and Kitimat Village; another of Pitt Island and Gull Island. The diary entries, which record Downie's traveling arrangements and his observations, are written from Victoria, Fort Rupert, Fort Simpson, Nasse, Bellacoola, Knight's Inlet, and other British Columbia sites.
Two diaries from 1861 Jul 4 to Aug 9 describe Downie's and Alexander McDonald's joint exploration of British Columbia's interior, beginning at Bute Inlet and following the Homathko River, in an unnsuccessful search for a route that would link the Pacific coast to the Fraser River. A printed 1866 diary completed in manuscript records Downie's stay in Portland, his steamer voyage to San Francisco and return to Oregon, and his subsequent travels through Washington State and B.C.'s Okanagan Valley. The latter part of the diary records difficult working conditions at Wild Horse Creek in the East Kootenays where Downie set up camp to mine gold alongside Chinese miners.
Series II. Correspondence consists of 8 letters to and from friends, officials, and business associates, documenting Downie's mining and business interests, his political opinions, and his relationship with the Canadian government as an independent explorer and a participant in British Columbia's gold mining industry. A letter from the editor of Downie's memoir, Chris M. Waage, describes work on the volume.
Series III. Writings and Other Papers includes manuscript documents concerning placer mining in British Columbia, infrastructure of the Queen Charlotte Island mines, an 1870 duel involving a member of the Know Nothing party in Downieville, California, and the Pioneer Association of B.C. A manuscript map of property leased in 1881 by the Quesnelle Mining Company, showing the site of a proposed dam on the Quesnelle River, and a manuscript ledger (528 p.) with most entries dated 1863 are present.
Series IV. Printed Works consists primarily of materials concerning British Columbia and the province's mining industry.
Series V. Visual Materials is organized into three subseries: Drawings, Photographs, and Postcards. The Photograph subseries includes photographs of individual Native Americans, including one indigenous youth in a military uniform, as well as a portrait of a group prepared for potlatch, and a portrait of William Downie.
The 2006 Addition (Box 4) consists of correspondence, photographs and printed material relating to William Downie and the Downie family.
Chinese -- British Columbia; Dueling -- California -- Downieville; Gold mines and mining -- British Columbia; Indians of North America -- British Columbia; Mines and mineral resources -- British Columbia; British Columbia -- Description and travel; British Columbia -- Discovery and exploration; British Columbia -- Politics and government; Downieville (Calif.) -- Politics and government; Fort Alexandria (B.C.); Fort Simpson (N.W.T.) -- Description and travel; Fraser River (B.C.) -- Description and travel; Kootenay Region (B.C.) -- Description and travel; Newcastle (Calif.); Okanagan River Valley (B.C. and Wash.) -- Description and travel; Port Essington (B.C.); Portland (Or.) -- Description and travel; Haida Gwaii (B.C.); Quesnel River (B.C.); San Francisco (Calif.) -- Description and travel; Skeena River (B.C.) -- Description and travel; Washington (State) -- Description and travel; Account books -- California -- Newcastle -- 19th century; Diaries -- British Columbia -- 19th century; Maps (documents) -- British Columbia -- Quesnel River -- 19th century; Photographs -- British Columbia -- 19th century; Scrapbooks; Explorers -- British Columbia -- 19th century; Gold miners; Bulkeley, E.; Downie, William, 1819-1893; Duncan, William, 1832-1918; Lippincott, Charles E.; MacDonald, Calvin B.; McDonald, Alexander; Tevis, Robert; Waage, Chris; E.H. Booth and Company; Pioneer Association of B.C; Quesnelle Mining Company; Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition ( 1909 Seattle, Wash.); Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show
- Diaries, 1859-1874; Series I; 0.11; (.25 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Diaries is arranged chronologically.
  - Diary, [1858?] Jan-Sep (Box 1, Folder a)
  - Diary, 1859 Sep 10-Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Register, manuscript diary, 1860 Feb 17-Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Diary, 1860 Apr 18-22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1861 Jul 4-21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1861 Jul 22-Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1861-1893; Series II; 0.11; (.25 box)
  Series II. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Young, William A. G., Colonial Secretary's Office, Vancouver Island, 1861 Jan, May (Box 1, Folder 5a)
    Concerning Downie's application for a naval vessel to protect his partners, prospecting along the Northern Coast
  - ALS to Colonel E. Bulkeley, Victoria, B.C., 1865 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Schofield, R. J., Umatilla, Oregon, 1865 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
    Encloses two notes from Schofield: an order to "Miss Hett" for an oil colour box, and an ALS to Alex Hett of Kent, England, introducing Downie
  - ALS to the "Editor of the Leader," Downieville, California, 1874 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hunter, Joseph, Nevada, California, 1881 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    Description of lease property located by the South Fork of Quesnell Mining Company, B.C.
  - Robson, John. Minister of Mines, Victoria, B.C., 1886 Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    Acknowledgement of receipt of 1886 Aug 6 report on gold mining operations in B.C.
  - Douglas, P. B., Assistant Secretary, Department of the Interior, Ottawa, Canada, 1886 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    Enclosing memorandum dated 1886 Sep 15 from George M. Dawson, Acting Director of the Geological Survey regarding Downie's offer to assist in exploration of the B.C. coast
  - Waage, Chris M., 1893 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings and Other Papers, 1859-1870; Series III; 1.4; (1.25 boxes)
  Series III. Writings and Other Papers is arranged chronologically.
  - Downie, William. "Memos. referring to mining in British Columbia," manuscript, 1859 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 7e)
  - "Rules and registers of the Queen Charlotte Island mines," manuscript draft, 1859 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ledger, manuscript, kept by John Shofer and for the accounts of Booth and Company, 1863-[19??] (Box 3, Folder 7g)
    Half of ledger used as scrapbook
  - MacDonald, Calvin B. "The Bloody Code: The Story of a Duel near Downieville in July 1855," manuscript, 1870 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Plan of ground leased by the South Fork of Quesnelle Mining Co.," manuscript map, [1881?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pioneer Association of B.C. "Constitution," manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Printed Works, 1859-1884; Series IV; 0.1; (.25 box)
  Series IV. Printed Works is arranged chronologically.
  - British Columbia. Laws, statutes, etc. Proclamation, 1859 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Occasional Paper. Two letters from the Bishop of Columbia to the Rev. E. Cridge and Bishop Demers, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Forbes, Charles. Prize Essay. Vancouver Island: its resources and capabilities..., [1862] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Waddington, Alfred. Bute Inlet Wagon Road Company Limited, prospectus, 1863 Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Vancouver Island Exploring Expedition. Vancouver Island: exploration, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Footlight, Virginia City, Nev. leaflet, 1876 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The South Fork of Quesnelle Mining Company, prospectus and bill, 1881, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Canada. Dept. of Agriculture. Province of British Columbia: Information for Intending Settlers, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - MacDonald, Calvin B. Echoes of Wartime, handbill, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Visual Materials, 1868-1909; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series V. Visual Materials is organized into three subseries: Drawings, Maps, and Postcards. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - Drawings
    - "Mt. Seymour Queen Charlotte Isl. from Congitz Cove," pencil drawing, 1868 Jun (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Verso: "Cacutyah," "Cutyah," and "Scailus, Petty Chief", sketched pencil portraits
  - Photographs
    - "Major Downie of Downieville, Cal.", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Potlatch - Alberni," group portrait of 17 Native celebrants, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Verso caption: "E. C. Brooks, Nanaimo, B.C."
    - Cartes-de-visites of Native Americans (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Postcards
    - "Buffalo Bill's Wild West," fold-out, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Eskimo Belles and Sled Reindeer, Alaska" (Box 2, Folder 25)
- 2006 Addition, 1859-1906; 0.42; (1 box)
  The 2006 Addition consists of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and one manuscript relating to William Downie and the Downie family. Correspondence consists of a letter of introduction for William Downie from Allen Francis, U.S. Consul in Victoria, British Columbia, and letters from the California State Library to Flora Downie Plantz. Undated (nineteenth century) photographs depict unidentified individuals. Printed material includes a heavily annotated Bible, two issues of The Rural Californian (Los Angeles, California), and newspaper clippings from San Francisco and Victoria, British Columbia in the 1880s and 1890s. Also included is a manuscript on quartz mining regulations by William Downie (1859).
  - Correspondence, 1866, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Printed material, 1861-1893, undated (Box 4, Folder 29-33)
  - "Mining regulations," manuscript, 1859 March (Box 4, Folder 34)
- OVERSIZE, 1.3; (1 box)
  - Plan of ground leased by the South Fork of the Quesnelle Mining Company, [1881?] (Box bsd, folder 26)